<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="somax.filter" module="somax" kind="patcher">

    <digest>
        Filters specific segments (events) of a corpus loaded into a <o>somax.player</o> based on descriptors and labels.
    </digest>

    <description>
        The <o>somax.filter</o> object allows filtering of segments (events) within a corpus that has been loaded into a <o>somax.player</o>. Filtering is based on descriptors and labels, allowing fine-grained selection of custom material.
    </description>

    <!--METADATA-->
    <metadatalist>
        <metadata name="author">ircam</metadata>
        <metadata name="tag">somax</metadata>
    </metadatalist>

    <!-- ARGUMENTS -->
    <objarglist>
        <objarg name="#1" optional="1" type="symbol">
            <digest>
                Filter name
            </digest>
            <description>
                The optional first argument sets the <m>name</m> of the <o>somax.filter</o>.
                <br />
                If no name is provided, the default name is <m>Filter</m>. 
                <br />
                Unless <m>uniquename</m> is set to <m>0</m>, the name will be formatted as <m>#0_Name</m>.
            </description>
        </objarg>
    </objarglist>

    <!--MESSAGES-->
    <methodlist>
        <method name="initialize">
            <digest>Initialize a filter connected to a player.</digest>
            <description>
                The <m>initialize</m> message will instantiate the <o>somax.filter</o> if this is correctly connected to the first outlet of a <o>somax.player</o>, or to the last outlet of a <o>somax.player.app</o>. 
                <br />
                At the same time, the signal from the first outlet of the <o>somax.filter</o> should be connected to the first inlet of the <o>somax.player</o> or <o>somax.player.app</o>.         
            </description>
        </method>
        <method name="label">
            <arglist><arg name="label_value" optional="0" type="symbol" /></arglist>
            <digest>Set label to match until further notice.</digest>
            <description>
                The <m>label</m> message sets the label to match and filter accordingly. 
                <br />
                When influencing with labels, they are simply referred to as "label" without specifying a descriptor name.
            </description>
        </method>
        <method name="openwindow">
        	<arglist><arg name="input" optional="0" type="int" /></arglist>
            <digest>Open the <o>somax.filter</o> user interface</digest>
			<description>
                Open the <o>somax.filter</o> window. This window will give you access to the list of available descriptors, from which you could select the active one.    
            </description>
        </method>
        <method name="terminate">
            <digest>Delete the filter from the connected player.</digest>
            <description>
                When an object is deleted, the patch cords are removed before the object itself, preventing freebangs from being received by connected objects.
                <br />
                Since communication between <o>somax.filter</o> and <o>somax.player</o> happens through patch cords, deleting the object does not automatically remove the filter from the player. 
                <br />
                The <m>terminate</m> message must be sent manually before deleting the <o>somax.filter</o> to ensure proper cleanup.
            </description>
        </method>
    </methodlist>

    <!--ATTRIBUTES-->
    <attributelist>
        <attribute name="autoinitialize" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
        	<digest>Enable/Disable autoinitialization of the filter.</digest>
            <description>
                By default the <o>somax.filter</o> will be automatically initalized when created. Set this attribute to <m>0</m> to disable this behaviour. 
            </description>
        </attribute>
        <attribute name="descriptor" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
    		<digest>Specify a descriptor name for filtering.</digest>
    		<description>
        		This attribute <m>descriptor descriptorname</m> is used to set a specific descriptor to filter. The argument <m>descriptorname</m> currently supports only labels.
        		<br />
       			It is possible to assign a descriptor even if it is invalid at the time of assignment, which is useful for pre-configuring the system before the player or server is started. 
       			<br />
        		The descriptor can be persistent across different corpora, ensuring that if the feature is switched or reloaded, the descriptor value remains consistent.
        		In cases where the specified descriptor is not available in the current corpus, a warning will be generated in the terminal or dump output.
        		<br />
        		If a corpus does not support the requested descriptor, the associated <o>somax.filter</o>'s eligibility will be set to 0, disabling it.
    		</description>
		</attribute>
        <attribute name="enabled" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
            <digest>Enable/Disable the filter.</digest>
            <description>
                The message <m>enabled 1</m> will enable the <o>somax.filter</o>. The message <m>enabled 0</m> will disable it.
            </description>
        </attribute>
        <attribute name="uniquename" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
    		<digest>Enable/Disable unique name for filter.</digest>
    		<description>
        		This attribute controls whether the filter name should be unique. By default, the <m>uniquename</m> is set to <m>1</m>, indicating that the filter name should be unique.
        		 <br />
        		To ensure uniqueness, prepend <m>#0_</m> to the filter name. If set to <m>0</m>, the filter name will not be enforced as unique.
    		</description>
		</attribute>
    </attributelist>

    <!--SEEALSO-->
    <seealsolist>
        <seealso name="somax.atom" />
        <seealso name="somax.player" />
        <seealso name="somax.player.app" />
        <seealso name="somax.audiocorpusbuilder" />
    </seealsolist>

</c74object>
