<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="somax.player" module="somax" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Monitor and control different regions to navigate the corpus
	</digest>

	<description>
		The somax.regions module should be connected in a loop with the somax.player and is used to monitor the playback and to dynamically interact with the corpus to guide the generation of the next event.
		Regions can be edited, enabled, disabled and resized according to your needs, providing precise and dynamic selection of different sections of the corpus, and offering tools to structure your interaction.  

	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">ircam</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">somax</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="buffername" optional="1" type="symbol">
			<digest>
				Buffer name
			</digest>
			<description>
                This mandatory argument sets the <m>name</m> of the <o>buffer~</o> used by the somax.audiorecord to record the audio input in.
				<br />
                When using somax.regions through a bpatcher, buffer name should be configured in the Max Inspector, by setting Argument(s) to @buffername name_of_your_buffer.
                <br /> 
                What happens if there's no argument?
			</description>
		</objarg>
    </objarglist>    

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
        
        <method name="editable">
			<arglist><arg name="input" optional="0" type="int" /></arglist>
			<digest>Select the region to edit</digest>
			<description>
                The message <m>editable</m> followed by an <o>int</o> between 1 and 6 sets the corresponding region as editable.         
            </description>
		</method>

        <method name="enabled">
            <arglist><arg name="input" optional="0" type="int" /></arglist>
            <digest>Enable/Disable regions</digest>
            <description>
                The message <m>enabled</m> is used to enable or disable a specific region. The syntax is <m>enabled index state</m>, where <m>index</m> is the number of the region (between 1 and 6) you want to enable or disable, and <m>state</m> is 1 if enabled, 0 if disabled.
                <br />
                Regions can be enabled or disabled one at a time (i.e., the message <m>enabled 1 0</m> will disable region 1), or by sending compound <m>enabled</m> messages separated by a comma.
            </description>
        </method>

        <method name="reset">
            <arglist><arg name="input" optional="0" type="int" /></arglist>
            <digest>Reset regions</digest>
            <description>
                The message <m>reset</m> followed by an <o>int</o> between 1 and 6 reset the corresponding region to its original size.
                <br />
                The message <m>reset</m>, without any argument, resets all the six regions to their default values, equally dividing them according to the corpus's length. 
            </description>
        </method>

        <method name="bounds">
            <arglist><arg name="input" optional="0" type="int" /></arglist>
            <digest>Set regions bounds</digest>
            <description>
                The message <m>bounds</m> sets the bounds, and thus the size, of a specific region.
                <br />
                The syntax is <m>bounds index start_ms end_ms</m> where <m>index</m> is the number of the region (between 1 and 6) and <m>start_ms</m> and <m>end_ms</m> are the start and end time (in ms) of the region. 
                <br />
                I.e., the message <m>bounds 1 0. 6000.</m> will resize region 1 with start bound at 0 ms and end bound at 6000 ms, selecting the first 6 seconds of the corpus.
            </description>
        </method>

	</methodlist>

    <!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
    
	</attributelist>
	
	
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="somax.player.app" />
		<seealso name="somax.server" />
		<seealso name="somax.audiorenderer" />
		<seealso name="somax.midirenderer" />
		<seealso name="somax.audioinfluencer" />
        <seealso name="somax.midiinfluencer" />
        <seealso name="somax.audiocorpusbuilder" />
        <seealso name="somax.midicorpusbuilder" />
        <seealso name="somax.audiorecord" />
	</seealsolist>
	
</c74object>